<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles conteining the request presented to the French Kyng by  the deputies of the reformed churches of the cou[n]trey of Languedoc and other  places adioyning, assembled by His Maiesties commaundement also an other request to him presented by the persons of the third estate of    the cou[n]trey of Prouence, vvith His Maiesties answere to the sayd requests :  also an aunswere of the Lord Lodouic Counte of Nassau to the aduertisements giuen him from the Kyng / translated out of French.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1574</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05065</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15206.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4732</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23831673</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23831673</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26896</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05065)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26896)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1835:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles conteining the request presented to the French Kyng by  the deputies of the reformed churches of the cou[n]trey of Languedoc and other  places adioyning, assembled by His Maiesties commaundement also an other request to him presented by the persons of the third estate of    the cou[n]trey of Prouence, vvith His Maiesties answere to the sayd requests :  also an aunswere of the Lord Lodouic Counte of Nassau to the aduertisements giuen him from the Kyng / translated out of French.</title>
                  <author>Charles IX, King of France, 1550-1574.</author>
                  <author>Eglises réformées de France.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[83] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henry Middleton, for Thomas Cadman,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1574.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-K⁴ L².</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Eglises réformées de France.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Wars of the Huguenots, 1562-1598.</term>
               <term>Languedoc (France) --  Church history.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26896:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26896:1"/>
            <p>Articles conteining the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt preſented to the French Kyng by the Deputies of the reformed Churches of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey of Langue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doc and other places adioyning, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled by his Maieſties commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</p>
            <p>Alſo an other requeſt to him preſented by the perſons of the third eſtate of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of Prouence, VVith his Maieſtie anſwere to the ſayd re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts.</p>
            <p>Alſo an aunſwere of the Lord Lodouic Counte of Naſſau to the aduertiſements giuen him from the Kyng.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of French.</p>
            <p>Jmprinted at London by Henry Middelton, for Thomas Cadman.</p>
            <p>Anno. 1574.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="petition_to_the_French_king">
               <pb facs="tcp:26896:2"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:26896:2"/>
               <head>¶ Articles preſented to the Kyng by the Deputies of the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches of the countrey of <hi>Languedoc,</hi> and other places adioyning. VVith the Kyngs anſwere.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>we the Vicounts,</hi> Barons, Gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and other here vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, making profeſſion of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion, both in our owne name particularly and of our adherents, &amp; alſo as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons deputed by the reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches of the countreyes of <hi>Guyenne, Viuaraiz, Giuaudan,</hi> the Seneſhalſee of <hi>Tholouze, Auuergne, Rouergue,</hi> hie and baſe <hi>Marche, Quercy, Perigord, Limoſin, Agennois, Armaignac, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manges, Conſerans, Bigorre, Albi</hi> and <hi>Foys, Lauragais, Albigeois,</hi> the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys of <hi>Caſtres, Villelongue, Mirepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ix, Carcaſſois,</hi> and other Prouinces
<pb facs="tcp:26896:3"/> adioyning, aſſembled by the permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and vnder the ſafe conductes of my Lord the Kyng of <hi>Polonia</hi> your Maſtieſties brother, in the town of <hi>Montauban:</hi> Hauing peruſed ſundry letters miſſiue of your Maieſtie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning declaration of your good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and will to reeſtabliſhe and maintaine a good and firme peace in this Realme, to performe the parts of your Royall office to al your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, and namely to thoſe of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, whom your Maieſtie willeth and meaneth from henceforth to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace &amp; entreat with all fauor, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and in the right of true and naturall ſubiects, and to take order by way of iuſtice for the requeſt that by them ſhalbe made and preſented moſt humbly to your Maieſtie, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching all the particulars that to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall ſeeme to be requiſite and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the maintaining of a true &amp; ſincere peace: We proteſt to this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,
<pb facs="tcp:26896:3"/> and with al our hart make moſt humble petition of that which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, vnder the inſtant and oft re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peted promiſes of my Lorde your Brother the Kyng of <hi>Polonia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt we proteſt before God &amp; his Angels, that it neuer entred into our harts, before theſe laſt troubles, nor ſince, to take awaye nor with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your Maieſtie our duties of moſt humble, moſt obedient, and faithfull ſubiection: But with true and firme loyaltie of ſubiectes wee haue alway acknowledged &amp; do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that it is our vocation and naturall eſtate by the ordinance of God, to yeeld to your maieſtie all things due by a faithfull ſubiect to his Kyng and ſoueraigne Lord.</p>
               <p>If that your Maieſtie haue taken in euil part and in diſpleaſure that which by vs hath bene done, prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, and executed, ſince the moneth of Auguſt 1572 vntil this preſent:
<pb facs="tcp:26896:4"/> we moſt humbly beſech you to cal to mind your letters of declaration da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the xxiiii. day of the ſayd month, and to haue in your moſt wiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration the moſt iuſt occaſions y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue by force &amp; conſtraynt compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vs to take weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in hand, with all other thinges requiſite to a iuſt and neceſſarie defence: to turne your eyes to the poore deceſſed perſones ſlaughtered and cruely put to death in ſondrie townes &amp; places of youre realme, vnder the pretence of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie, but truly in hatred of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed religion: &amp; that it will pleaſe you in pitie to looke vppon the ſmal remna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t eſcaped out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a true remorſe &amp; compaſſion of a father of your countrie: to enter into your ſelfe and deeply and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely to behold y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> benefit that your Maieſtie receiueth of the ſingular and wonderfull goodnes of God: and there vppon to meruell with vs
<pb facs="tcp:26896:4"/> aſwel of our preſeruation, as of this ouerture of peace in youre realme, like as a good Father would doe in his howſe, when after that he hath beholden in his howſe ſome of his naturall children murdered before his face, and his whole familie in ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifeſt danger of vtter ruine, he doth at length ſee by the grace of god all the reſt of his children and his houſe reſtored to a good peaceable and ſure eſtate.</p>
               <p>If it ſhalbe by any man thought e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and vnmeete for the greatneſſe of your royall eſtate, to make open declaration and proteſtation of ſuch a griefe, ſurely (vnder the fauor and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orrection of ſuch as ſo thinketh) ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o thinke ſhould be to do ſo much y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more wrong, firſt to God, and after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o your owne conſcience, to your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or and ſuertie, and to your iuſtice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd office royall, and to throw vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oure ſubiects profeſſing the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:26896:5"/> aſwel thoſe that be murdered as theſe that be left alyue, an euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing infamie ioyned with reproch of a pretenced conſpiracie and rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wherunto, next after the ſeruice of God we ought to haue regard a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue al other things that be nedeful for vs, for by ſuch mean, alſo ſhuld in plaine termes and openly be iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed aſwell the authors as executers of thoſe murders, which ſhould be to vs reprochfull and impoſſible to be diſſemblingly paſſed ouer.</p>
               <p>And therfore, for the firſt article of our requeſt, we holding vs to youre Letter of the 24. of Auguſt, do moſt humbly beſeche your Maieſtie, that folowing the courſe that was begon vppon the hurt of the late Counte <hi>de Coligny</hi> Admirall of <hi>France,</hi> it wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pleaſe you according to the purport of your ſayd Letter, to do exemplar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> iuſtice vpon the ſayd murders, by vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſuſpected Iudges thereto ſpecially
<pb facs="tcp:26896:5"/> apoynted, of like and equall number of both religions, and namely other then thoſe of the courtes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes and Preſidencies of <hi>Paris, Tholouze, Bordeaux, Rouen, Orleans,</hi> and <hi>Lyon,</hi> in which the principall preſidents and councellers are repu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted to haue bene the fauorers appro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uers &amp; practiſers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, at leaſt of thoſe that haue bene co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted within their townes, yea and within your priſons, and at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen aſſemblies: and with as greate ſpede as may be, to depute &amp; apoynt the ſayd Iudges in all places wher it ſhalbe nedfull, enioyning them vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pon a great paine to proceed therin ſpedely, diligenly &amp; vprightly, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out maintenance, without parciall wyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king and deſembling of Iuſtice: for ſo ſhall your Maieſtie begin to pull out of the hartes of your ſubiectes that be of the religion, the iuſt and great diſtruſte that they haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="tcp:26896:6"/> by ſeing themſelues giuen vp &amp; abandoned to the crueltie of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, and ſo ſhal they the more ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dely take to them ſelues occaſion to truſt in your onely worde and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</p>
               <p>Alſo it may pleaſe your Maieſtie to remember that in certaine youre Letters of inſtructions and declara<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions, ſent to the gouerners &amp; your Liefenantes of your prouinces, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> monethes of September, October, and December, there is ſpecially re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued the puniſhment of thoſe that ſhalbe found charged with the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed conſpiracy againſt the perſons of you and yours, and with intelly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, practiſes and conducting of matters done during the laſt peace, which thing might be a cauſe that vnder this falſe pretence of reſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, we or ſome of vs might be here after touched enquired vppon and moleſted in this realme iudicially or
<pb facs="tcp:26896:6"/> otherwiſe: And to mete with ſuche captious dealinges &amp; oppreſſions, it may pleaſe your maieſtie by expreſſe wordes to reuoke the ſayd reſeruati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, and declare that youre maieſtie holdeth and alwaye reputeth vs for good &amp; faythfull ſubiectes innocent and gyltleſſe of al conſpiracie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, with inhibition to your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocats &amp; atourneys gennerall, their ſubſtitutes and all other for euer, to make thervpon any purſute proceſſe mencion or reproch.</p>
               <p>That y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame declaration be made of the ſayde Lord Admirall, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie <hi>dela Roche-foucaut,</hi> the Ladies <hi>de Briquemaut</hi> and <hi>Cauaignes,</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that were murdered condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and put to death for the ſayde ſuppoſed conſpiracie. And that all areſtes and Iudgments giuen, and all procedinges had or paſſed vnder that pretence, againſt thoſe ot the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligion, be reuerſed, adnulled, and
<pb facs="tcp:26896:7"/> declared to be of no effect and value, and to haue bene geuen vpon falſe &amp; ſclanderous information, and that the perſons deceſſed ſhalbe reſtored to their good renounes, and their heires to their goods and rights of inheritance: And that their children which for hatred to their fathers are impriſoned, or put or holden in any other diſtreſſe, be ſpedely deliuered, and reſtored to their former honor &amp; libertie into the hands of their next friendes. And to ordeyne that thoſe to whome their eſtates, dignities, charges, and offices, ſubiect to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances haue bene giuen, ſhall be bound to pay the finance to the ſayd heyres as ſhall be awarded by two of the kindred or friendes knowen, and neuertheleſſe that their goodes &amp; money taken ſhalbe reſtored them, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> withholders conſtrayned there vnto by all wayes of iuſtice.</p>
               <p>That likewiſe al declarations, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunces,
<pb facs="tcp:26896:7"/> and rules made againſt thoſe of the Religion ſince the xxiiii. of Auguſt laſt paſt, be reuerſed, reuo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked and declared of no effect and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue.</p>
               <p>And to extinguiſh the memorie of the ſaid iudgements and arreſtes &amp; the execution of them, that likewiſe the ſayd declarations, ordinances, &amp; rules be raſed and withdrawne out of all regiſters of Courtes as well ſoueraigne as inferior, and that the ſame iudgements, arreſtes, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutions, declarations, ordinances, and rules be taken away, cancelled &amp; defaced: That alſo all monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, markes, and tokens of the ſaid exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions be deſtroyed, together with the Bookes and infamous actes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the perſonages, memory and poſteritie of the ſaid perſons decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and executed, and that namely &amp; ſpecially ſhalbe defaced ſuppreſſed &amp; (as much as ſhalbe requiſite) there
<pb facs="tcp:26896:8"/> ſhalbe prohibited all proceedinges, generall and ordinary, as well by arreſt of the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> in memorie of the ſaid ſlaughters, as by an other arreſt of <hi>Tholouze,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſed by arreſt of you priuie coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell touching the taking of the town houſe in the ſayd firſt troubles, and that all bee done in the preſence of foure ſpeciall perſons, whereof two ſhalbe of the Religion, hauing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in the ſame during the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> record examplified word by word of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proceeding herein ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be expedited and deliuered to thoſe which ſhall haue expreſſe charge of procuration for that intent.</p>
               <p>That it be declared that thoſe of the Religion, haue iuſtly and vpon good occaſion taken armes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawen them ſelues &amp; made warre in theſe laſt troubles, as being ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrained by violence done, wher with they haue ben terrified and put in feare.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26896:8"/>
               <p>And foraſmuch as by the hearing of the word, and by Eccleſiaſtical diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline your ſubiects are the better bolden in dutie of their ſubiection, firſt toward God, and next to your Maieſtie, and to their other ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors whom it hath pleaſed you to ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>point ouer them, they moſt humbly &amp; with moſt entire affection beſeech your Maieſtie in this behalfe to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt of your fauour, and therin to ordeine that of your graunt and perpetuall benefite, the exerciſe of their Religion, and Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Diſcipline, and namely of their Synodes, conferences, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtories Eccleſiaſticall be freely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for euer, &amp; in all parts of this Realme, as well publikely, as priuately, compriſing therin by ſpeciall name the libertie of honeſt &amp; ſeemely burial without difference of time, in the ſame common Church-yardes, about which matter many
<pb facs="tcp:26896:9"/> of the Catholiques haue oftentimes ſtirred vp great riots and debates in the townes where the ſayd exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe was not permitted. And that al exemptions from the exerciſe of the ſayd Religion, limitted in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> townes and places as well of the Queene your Maieſties honorable mother, as of my Lord the Kyng of <hi>Polonia</hi> your Maieſties Brother, and other within your dominion, be reuoked &amp; declared fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> henceforth of no effect.</p>
               <p>And to preuent all ſuſpiſcions y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> oftentimes heretofore haue bene raiſed touching the collectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s made &amp; leuied among thoſe of the religion for the charges and maintenance of the eccleſiaſticall miniſterie. It may pleaſe your maieſty from henceforth to exempt thoſe of the religion from the payment of tithes in thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where the ſayd exerciſe ſhall be, for as much as the tithes of their owne nature are apoynted for the ſayd miniſterie.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26896:9"/>
               <p>That none of the religion ſhall be ſommoned or conſtrayned by youre officers, vniuerſities, colledges and Comunalties, to any ceremonie and contribution contrary to the ſayd re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligion, and that ſo much as the caſe ſhall require there be expreſſe prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bicion in your courtes and vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in any wiſe to exact of them at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyning to any office and degre, the othes accuſtomed in the churche of <hi>Rome</hi> contrarie to their ſayd religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>That all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſes rents and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes of colledges and ſcholes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted for the inſtruction of youth ſhalbe accompted and holden as or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned for euer for your ſubiects y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> will be there receiued, without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king difference of religion, neyther as touching the Rector or Regent, nor for the Scholers and officers, conſultes of townes &amp; places: wher the ſayd ſcholers and Colledges
<pb facs="tcp:26896:10"/> ſhall be bound to receiue rectors, &amp; regents of both religions, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>faction &amp; inſtruction of both ſortes without fraud or parcialitie.</p>
               <p>That the mariages of Prieſtes &amp; Eccleſiaſticall perſons that now bee or hereafter ſhalbe of the ſaid Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, be declared lawfull, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe their children iſſuing of their mariage for their inheritance and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rights of lawfull legitimation: And that as well the father as the children be declared capable of pub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>like offices eſtates and adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>That the deciding of mariages, that is to ſay, whether they be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and perfect or no, ſhalbe from henceforth determined by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtories and others of the religion, or at leaſt by their ſuperior Iudge of your Iuſtice being a man of the ſame Religion.</p>
               <p>That the gardians of Orphanes
<pb facs="tcp:26896:10"/> whoſe father was of the Religion ſhalbe bound to cauſe them to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed and taught in the Religion of their Fathers, at the leaſt vntill their age of diſcretion, like as your Maieſtie hath at other time hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ordained.</p>
               <p>That the ſame benefit of the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of the Religion be accorded and ordained to the inhabitants and dwellers that be of the Religion in the Countie of <hi>Veniſſe,</hi> and the Arch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>biſhopricke of <hi>Auignon:</hi> And that it pleaſe your Maieſtie to doe ſo much with the Kyng of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> that all thinges maye abide in <hi>Nauarre</hi> and <hi>Bearne</hi> in the ſame eſtate as the late Queene of <hi>Nauarre</hi> his mother left them at the time of hir deceaſſe: &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo to treat ſo with the Pope &amp; Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Auignon</hi> that your graunt and good pleaſure in this behalfe may be confirmed and approued in due forme, ſpecially for the reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:26896:11"/> and full recompence of the goods of thoſe of the ſayd Countie of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the Frenchmen which haue borne Armes with thoſe of <hi>Bearne,</hi> may enioye the profit and benefit of this Edict.</p>
               <p>As touching the adminiſtration of iuſtice, it may pleaſe your Maieſtie to conſider the demeanors of youre courts of Parliament againſt thoſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> religion, ſpecially in your towne of <hi>Tholouze,</hi> wherby may be iudged what is and alway may be their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention. For this cauſe, it may bee your good pleaſure to aſſigne them iudges vnſuſpected, and to ordaine that all proces betwene parties of two religions ſhalbe iudged as wel in caſes ciuill, as criminall, in inſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces as well ſuperior, as inferior, by equal number of iudges, wherof the halfe ſhalbe Catholique, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Religion: and where all
<pb facs="tcp:26896:11"/> the parties bee of one religion, that there all the iudges likewiſe may be taken and appoynted of the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, except ſuch as bee ſuſpected. And that for this intent there be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined one chamber or court for the reſort of euery Parliament, and one peaceable and vnſuſpected town for thoſe of the Religion.</p>
               <p>That all prouiſions and declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s obtained during theſe troubles and ſince the 24. of Auguſt laſt by the Catholikes, againſt ſuch ſentences iudgements and arreſtes as vppon learning of the parties, and in time of peace haue bene giuen for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of thoſe of the Religion, ſhalbe reuoked and delayed of no effect and value, as obteined by ſtealth, the ſayd arreſts remaining in their full force &amp; vertue executorie, according to your ordinances, although thoſe that haue had the ſaid arreſts haue bene perſons Eccleſiaſticall of the
<pb facs="tcp:26896:12"/> Church of Rome.</p>
               <p>That all ſeates of iuſtice that of olde time and before the troubles, haue ben holden in the towns now preſently poſſeſſed by thoſe of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ſhalbe there continued: or if they haue ben remoued, they may be reſtored &amp; brought thither againe: And generally that all thoſe of the Religion be reſtored, &amp; from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth without any ſtaye for circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of forme, fully placed againe in the exerciſe of their eſtates and dignities, charges and offices, as well of your Maieſtie as of inferior Seignories, and that al prouiſions to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary be reuoked, and other fees and penſions payed as well for the time paſt as for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time to come.</p>
               <p>And for aſmuch as diuers of the religion haue had by reſignation &amp; for money, according to the vſage of your permiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, certein offices either Iudiciall or other, alitle before the
<pb facs="tcp:26896:12"/> beginning of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſent trobles ſince which trobles being happened, the reſignes by reaſon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hatred borne to their religion, and for their iuſte feare of murder, haue not bene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to obtein the Letters of graunt nor to get the reſignator aducted of your Maiſtie. In the meane time ſome of them haue payd the fine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed wholy or in part, ſome other haue entred into bondes and giuen ſureties to paye within a ſhort time which time being incurred y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſureties haue ben conſtreyned to make pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is not reſonable: it may pleaſe your Maieſtie to declare the ſayd bondes and promiſes diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed and as not made, and ſo to ordein without hauing reſpect to the Iudg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments which poſſibly may haue ben giuen in the meane time: And that the ſayd iudgements alſo be declared voyd and of no efect. That the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney payed for theſe cauſes, whether
<pb facs="tcp:26896:13"/> it be to the reſigner or his heyres ſhalbe repayed to the reſignes being of the religion, being preuented by iuſt impedimentes. And where pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath not bene made, that in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> caſe there bond ſhall remaine not ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and exempt from conſtraint of Iuſtice.</p>
               <p>That theſe of the religion be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted and receiued indifferently to eſtates charges of offices aſwell iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial as other, without difference of religion, ſpecially of reſignes, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the receiuing and admitting of them ſhalbe exempte from other courtes, and reſerued to the chamber y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be erected for the iudgment of their Princes.</p>
               <p>That all preſcriptions either by conuenient cuſtome or Lawe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time may haue ben incurred du<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring &amp; ſince y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt troubles &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> later troubles that ſince haue happened, vntill this preſent ſhalbe deemed &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:26896:13"/> holden as not incurred.</p>
               <p>As touching policies, your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie may well haue vnderſtood how great diſorder and confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialitie, difference and diſtinction of perſons for Religion, hath brought in this behalfe in all townes and places where the Catholikes do in number and power exceede thoſe of the Religion, accompting them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way as degraded vnworthy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of publike charges and admi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſtrations: It may therfore be your good pleaſure beſide the declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s already made by all your Edictes as touching the capabilitie of thoſe of the Religion, and their common enioying and participation of thoſe charges, to ordeine that from hence forth in all the townes and places of this Realme the ſayd charges be diſtributed equally betweene the Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tholikes and theſe of the religion, and namely to auoide the ouerchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings
<pb facs="tcp:26896:14"/> of taxes forbidden by your Maieſtie.</p>
               <p>That thoſe of the religion remain quite and diſcharged for all their aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies aſwell generall as perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larlly eſtabliſhment of iuſtice, policy, and rule among them ſelues, iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and executions thereof, voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, treaties, negotiactions, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tractes made with all ſtrange prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and eſtates, and of all moneyes taken of your fiances and receiptes, coynages, mouables, debtes, arera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of rentes and reuenues, felling of woodes, ſale of goodes mouable, aſſeſſing of rentes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> immouables and rightes belonging to Ecleſiaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall perſones and other catholikes taxes, impoſitions of money and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinges, exactions and leuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges of the ſame, baylyes ranſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of priſoners, and of all other kindes of money which by occaſion of theſe trobles haue bene taken by
<pb facs="tcp:26896:14"/> them, of the ordeining of theſe that haue had commandement among them, or of counceles prouinciall &amp; poletike according to their rules, ſo as neyther they, nor thoſe that haue bene apoynted for the leueyeng and diſpoſition of the ſayd moneys mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uables &amp; other thinges aboueſayd, nor theſe that haue deliuered and furniſhed the ſame, may in any wiſe be anſwerable therfore now nor her after, but that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſumes to that effect payd by your ſayd officers &amp; others be alowed by your chambers of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comptes, treſorers of finances and others by vertue of this Edict with out other warrant.</p>
               <p>And that all perſons accomptant whether it be of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> receiptes by them eſtabliſhed or other dealing with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing what ſoeuer it be, ſhalbe bound to verifie theyr accomptes of their dealinges by thoſe that haue had generall authoritie ouer them,
<pb facs="tcp:26896:15"/> and to the ſayd councels prouincial. And that the like be done of all thoſe that haue had the handeling charge &amp; adminiſtration of money during the former trobles &amp; ſince the yeare 1567. And the remaine that ſhalbe found due by the ſayd accomptantes and other detters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd moneys ſhalbe employed to the acquital and diſcharge of thoſe of the religion for charges by occaſion of the trouble and maintenance of the warre. And this done, the ſayd accomptantes ſhall remaine acquited of their ſayd adminiſtration and dealinges, and wholy diſcharged thereof, bringing the aquitance of thoſe that had the commaunding of them in theſe laſt trobles made by the aduiſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd councels Prouincial and according to their rule, ſo as in time to come neyther they nor their ſucceſſors ſhall in any wiſe be put to anſwere therfore, forbidding to al your cham<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bers
<pb facs="tcp:26896:15"/> of accountes &amp; other Iudges ordinary or extraordinary all Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction and conuſance, and to youre attorneyes generall or perticular al power to ſue for the ſame. That alſo thoſe of the religion remaine acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and diſcharged for all actes of hoſtilitie, leuyeng and conducting of men of Warre, founding and taking of artilerie and munitions, making of pouder and ſaltpeter, takinges diſmantellinges and raſinges of townes and Caſtles, enterpriſes againſt the ſame, burninges and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyings of Churches and houſes, and fortifications and reparations of Townes &amp; places holden in their holding, &amp; generally of all that hath bene by them don and practiſed du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the aforeſayd and the former trobles although y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame be not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly expreſſed and declared, ſo as for any of the thinges aboueſayd nor other that haue happened in the
<pb facs="tcp:26896:16"/> ſayd trobles, none of them nor of their poſteritie in generall or in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular be charged nor in any wiſe reproched with any matter of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion Diſobedience or Treaſon, notwithſtanding all declarations, Edicts, and ordinances which your Maieſtie may haue made, to the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trarie and that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caſe, may be reuoked and declared of no effect and value, as wel in this reſpect as in reſpect of all other thinges proceding or depending vpon the ſayd trobles.</p>
               <p>That all thinges taken by priuat perſones without publike authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, Magiſtrate, Gouernoure, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſull, Captaine, or other by their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, or by the aſſemblies of the Comunalties on both parties, and againſt the rules of the ſayd aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, be reſtored to thoſe to whome they apertaine, if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> things be found remaining in their former kinde, and
<pb facs="tcp:26896:16"/> if not, then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> value by iuſte appraiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment. And as touching moue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables and other thinges taken by hoſtilitie, although they be found re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in their kinde, they ſhall not be chalenged nor ſubiect to reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titution.</p>
               <p>That the fruites of this preſent yeare that haue ben taken and leui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vntill the daye and date of theſe preſent Articles, be declared not to be ſubiect to any reſtitution on the one part or the other, to the intent to ſtope all variances &amp; proceſſe that by this occaſion may ariſe amonge your ſubiectes.</p>
               <p>That theſe of the Religion be not conſtrained nor drawen into y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lawe for payment of impoſitions ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and extraordinarie aſſeſſed by the Catholikes during the preſent and former trobles, but ſhall thereof re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine acquited and diſcharged.</p>
               <p>And for aſmuch as in all places
<pb facs="tcp:26896:17"/> where we haue warred for our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> charges haue bene ſo expreſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed and importable, that the moſte part of vs are greatly in detted and charged, It may pleaſe your Maieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to giue vs leaue to haue an impo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſition and taxe to be ſett among all vs of the Religion, at the leaſt to the ſome of ſixe ſcore thouſand poundes payable in two yeares to be employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the ful diſcharg of our ſayd def<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: And for the leuyeng thereof to grant vs neceſſary meanes of con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtraint as it were for youre owne money.</p>
               <p>It may pleaſe your Maieſtie to grant to thoſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Religion which in the trobles paſſed haue bought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing Temporall of Ecleſiaſticall perſons &amp; truly payd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> price therof, that they may continue the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and enioying of the thinges by them bought for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſſurance of their Money, vntill they be recompenced
<pb facs="tcp:26896:17"/> by the ſayd Eccleſiaſticall perſons or other y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> will or may redeme the ſame w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this condition y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhall leaue the poſſeſſion immediatly after ſuch repayment to them made.</p>
               <p>Now Sir, reſteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> principal point, namely the meanes of a true &amp; iuſte ſuretie for the holding, enduring, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance and perpetuall inuiola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mainteyning of your Maieſties promiſes and ordinances touching al the matters aboue ſayd by a firme and continuing peace, wherin we are moſt ſorie and much agreued to propounde, and to demaund of your Maieſtie by our moſt humble ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication ſuch meanes as ſeme to vs pertinent and reaſonable yea &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie to the eſtabliſhment for euer of a good and firme peace in this Realme. For we had rather that theſe meanes had bene offered vs of your Fatherly good will and fauor, and of your owne proper motion.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26896:18"/>
               <p>But for aſmuch as it pleaſeth your Maieſtie to permit vs and to do vs that honor to demaund it of you, we moſt humbly beſeech your goodnes that it be your good pleaſure, for the commoditie of your eſtate, the reſte of your conſience, the greatneſſe and aſſurance of this Crowne, and the common benefite and quiet of your Subiectes, to contracte an vnitie &amp; League of new promiſe, coniuncti, on, and Amitie to endure, with all the Princes Potentates and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of <hi>Almaigne</hi> and <hi>Swiſſerland</hi> that be of the Religion, and the Queenes of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> to this intent, with one common hand and conſent to maintaine vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie aſwell betwene them and their Subiectes, as betwene your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie and all your Subiectes entier<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly both thoſe that be called Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes and thoſe that be named of the Religion reformed, &amp; this to be don
<pb facs="tcp:26896:18"/> in all ciuile and humaine thinges. That al theſe allies promiſe &amp; ſwear to mayntaine y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd vnitie coniunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion and amitie for the common con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinuing of all in the ſayd eſtate and communitie of all Ciuile &amp; humaine thinges, in like manner as if they were all of one religion, and this to be done in euery eſtate of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries Landes and Seignories of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Kinges Princes Potentates or common weales.</p>
               <p>That they ſwere and promiſe that none of the ſayd Lordes Kinges or theyr ſucceſſors, Princes Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tats or common weales ſhal breake the ſayd vnitie, nor violate the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like faith and promiſſes as well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the ſayd allies as betwene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their ſubiectes: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoſe which ſhall obſerue it on their part, may by all wayes of force conſtraine him or them that ſhall doe to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. And that they be bound to do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26896:19"/> like at the only requeſt of thoſe who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſhall concerne, truely obſeruing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd vnitie, of whether ſoeuer religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they be.</p>
               <p>That for eſchewing a conſpiracy of a <hi>Sicilian</hi> euenſong) as they terme it) thoſe of the religion in this realm may haue by ſpeciall priueledge and graunt in perpetuitie, the keping of the townes and places which wee holde at this preſent, and alſo of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne other townes in euerye pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, ſuch as ſhalbe thought mete by the eight ſpeciall perſones indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently choſen by two that youre Maieſtie will depute and two that thoſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> religion ſhall name: which is to be done with expedicion at the place to be agreed vpon.</p>
               <p>That your Maieſties garriſons be placed onely in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> frontier townes and places where garriſons hath of ancient time bene vſed, or at the leaſt as farre of as well may be from
<pb facs="tcp:26896:19"/> the ſayd townes and places nowe preſently holden by thoſe of the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, be it in comming or going of the ſayd garriſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and that there be not lodged greater nomber of horſe with their armures without the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent of theſe of the religion, and that they come and ſeiourne ſo modeſtly, that thereof ariſe no ſuſpicion nor inconuenience.</p>
               <p>It may pleaſe your Maieſtie to take in good parte, that wee moſte humbly beſeeche you, that your Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours and Lieuetenants gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall that wil paſſe by or viſit the ſaid townes and places nowe holden by thoſe of the Religion, may not come thyther with force nor with great companie, than with their ordinarie and accuſtomed traine in tyme of peace, and that they be admoniſhed, ſo to behaue them ſelues in the ſaid townes and places, as thoſe of the Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may haue no occaſion ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb facs="tcp:26896:20"/> to enter into feare and ſuſpicion, And that the like be obſerued by the Lordes of the ſayde Townes and places.</p>
               <p>That nothing of the ſayd townes and places holden by thoſe of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion be raſed, that hath ben made for fortification, ſauing only ſo farre as they ſhall thinke it expedient for their ſuretie. And that there be not required or taken from them any of their munitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of warre or armour, whether it be artillary or other.</p>
               <p>And for the greater and better ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacie of your royall authoritie and good will to the vpright and ſincere obſeruation of the Articles of this peace: We moſt humbly beſech your Maieſtie that firſt in full aſſembly of your priuie counſell, and afterward in your court of Parliament of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> in full audience, by your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, the Queenes your moſt honora<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble mother &amp; ſpouſe, our ſoueraigne
<pb facs="tcp:26896:20"/> Ladies, my Lordes your brethred, and the Lords the Princes of your bloud, the Lordes Mareſchals of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and the counſellers of your priuie counſell, it be confirmed and ſworne that the Articles of this peace ſhalbe entirely mainteined, &amp; perpetually and faithfully obſerued. And that the like be done by al your preſidents, counſellers, aduocates, procurators or attorneys, and euery of them in all other your Courtes of Parliaments, and preſidencies.</p>
               <p>That for mutuall obſeruation of a perpetuall obedience and fidelitie, thoſe of the Religion throughout this Realme generally, together with the Catholikes, renue their othes offidelitie before your officers in their places, with enterchangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble condition and promiſe on both partes, neuer hereafter to commit any ſlaughters one againſt an other generally or particularly, by whom
<pb facs="tcp:26896:21"/> ſo euer the ſame bee commaunded, without exception: but to leaue the whole conuſance of crimes and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like reuenge to the courſe of youre lawes, as is agreed in theſe articles of peace.</p>
               <p>And to the intent to come by little and little to a true entier and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reconciliation of amitie among all your ſubiectes of both the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: We moſt humbly beſeech your Maiſtie to ordaine that euerie yere during fiue yeares the ſayd othe be renued, as well by the aſſemblies of the eſtates of euerie Prouince in one of the moſt peaceable townes in ech Prouince, as at other general aſſem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blies of the inhabitants of euery principal Towne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dioceſſe, which ſhall be holden at ſundry termes among thoſe of the two Religions, that is to ſay, in the principal aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie by the Deputies of either Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion aſwell of the nobilitie as of the
<pb facs="tcp:26896:21"/> comons of the whole prouince, and in the aſſembly of euery Dioces and Bayliwicke: wher they ſhal promiſe and ſwere not onely to keepe firme peace and amitie mutually, but alſo to employe their liues and goodes for your ſeruice, &amp; ſpecially to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine this vnitie and pacification a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all breakers and diſturbers thereof without any exception as is aboueſayd.</p>
               <p>Finally we hope that your Maieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſhall well like, that we your moſt humble and moſt obedient ſubiectes continue our ſtanding vppon our Garde, without doing any force or hoſtilitie, vnder the ſuſpencion and intermiſſion which it hath pleaſed your Maieſtie to enioyne vs.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Montauban,</hi> the vi. day of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. 1573. Thus ſigned, <hi>Paulin, Gourdon, Lomaſin. Verlhac, Ferrieres, Monſegon, Yollec, Breſſac, Sainct bon,
<pb facs="tcp:26896:22"/> Donzac, Derboras, B. de Narbonne, Stopuihart, Brecquet, Drephelipon, de la Source, Galheuſte, Sebin, de Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trech, P. de la Tour, Decluuier, P. Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, S. Chamayot, Corraire, Porcel, Payau, Rigord, de Robert, de l'Armoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, A. Nolhac, de Roſier, Vuiſaud, Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert, Auoum, du Port, Reuires, Royſſe, G. Moragnes, Pomyer, de Chaſtellet, de Voyau, du Cros, de Fulger, Degau, A. Gardes, du Poncet, du Buſquet, Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delſes, Merlein, Ymbert de la Place, G. Rodyer, I. Cabanie, Noheſau, Baches Deueunſin, de Noalhan.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="Kings_answer">
               <pb facs="tcp:26896:22"/>
               <head>The Kings aunſwere to the Deputies of the reformed Churches of the countrey of Languedoc and other places adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Kyng hauing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that to him haue bene made by thoſe of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion called reformed being ſent vnto his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, vſing toward them his clemencie and naturall goodnes, hath by mouth declared vnto them the aſſurance that they ought to haue of his good grace fauour and protection when they shall by the effectes shewe them ſelues ſuch towarde him as al good and loyall ſubiectes ought to be to their Prince: whereunto he hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently moued them by his laſt Edict, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the benefit wherof they haue all due ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of that which they haue alwaye shewed themſelues to deſire touching the exerciſe of their pretenſed Religion &amp; the ſuretie of their perſons &amp; goods. And for as much as they haue alway declared that they
<pb facs="tcp:26896:23"/> haue no other will but to ſatiſfie the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements of his ſayd Maieſtie, he hath thought good, for their better conformitie, to ſend the Duke de Vſes peere of Fraunce, and the Lord of Caplus Knight of his order to Monſieur de Dampuille Marshall of Fraunce his Gouernour and Lieutenant ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall in Languedoc, to ſaye to him on his Maieſties behalfe, that he chuſe ſome towne or place of his gouernement neere to Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauban, and which he shal thinke fitteſt for the purpoſe, and that he repaire thither, and there aduertiſe thoſe of the Religion called reformed, that they ſend thither the ſayd Deputies or other whom they will on their behalfe, for conference to be had with them by the ſayd Lord Marshall, touching their quiet, ſuretie, and preſeruation, and other things concerning and appertaining vnto the executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; obſeruing of the ſayd Edict, and alſo the courſe of law and iuſtice, which his Maieſtie meaneth to haue miniſtred vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to them with all vprightneſſe and equitie: Alſo to be aduiſed of ſuch procurations as shall be neceſſary for the particularities de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending vpon the ſayd caſe, to the end that by the xv. day of December, by which tyme his Maieſtie hopeth to be retourned to his towne of Compiegne from the voyage that
<pb facs="tcp:26896:23"/> he preſently maketh to the frontiers of his realme, for conducting his brother the king of Polonia going towardes his kingdome, his Maieſtie being then aduertiſed of the whole by the ſayd Lord Mareshal, may giue order as to him shall ſeeme neceſſarie. And where he is required by the ſayd deputies to prolong the ceaſsing of armes, his Maieſtie will write to the ſayde Lorde Mareshall, to cauſe all actes of hoſtilitie to ceaſe, prouided alwaye that they of the religion giue order on their part, that nothing bee atttempted to the contrary, as of late hath bene done, which his Maieſtie doth expreſly forbid.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>At Villiers-Cotterets, <date>the 18. day of October. 1573.</date>
                  </dateline> Thus ſigned,
<signed>CHARLES.</signed> And vnderneth.
<signed>FIZEL.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="petition_to_the_French_king">
               <pb facs="tcp:26896:24"/>
               <head>A requeſt exhibited to the <hi>King by the Deputies of the <hi>third eſtate of the Countries of</hi>
                  </hi> Languedocke, Dolphine, and Prouince.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Yr,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>before we we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in hande w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the charge that was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto vs by your moſt humble and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient ſubiectes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of the third eſtate of your cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie and Countie of <hi>Prouence, Folca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quier,</hi> &amp; the Landes bordering there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon, we wel foreſawe three poynts which would make our ſute odious or at leaſtwyſe not ſo well fauoured as we gladly would haue deſired, that we might returne into our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie with good ſpeed of the thing for which we come &amp; preſent our ſelues ſewters vnto your Maieſtie.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26896:24"/>
               <p>The firſt is, that it is an vnſeemly thing for Subiectes to inquire of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peculiar affaiers of their King, or to go about to demaund a reaſon why he doeth them. The Second is, that ſubiectes ought to haue a ſure good opinion of their Princes good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning towardes them, and that hee will not greue them with extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſubſidies, without great cauſe and vrgent neceſſitie, and therefore that the ſeſſing of them lieth not in the controlment of the Subiectes. The third is, that it is an vnſeemly and intolerable raſhnes of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iectes, to intend to brydle or reſtrain the affaires of the ſtate, wherof they haue no knowlege but ſuperficially and by coniecture. And in very deed theſe three poyntes haue made vs to refuſe our commiſſion often tymes, &amp; we had not condeſcended to haue receiued it, but for three other conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations that were layed afore vs
<pb facs="tcp:26896:25"/> in the aſſembly of the three eſtates, held in the Moneth of Iuly laſt paſt in your town of <hi>Aix.</hi> One was the conſideration of your natural good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and clemencie, ſufficiently ſhew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed by experience towardes your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, where through we ought to hope for gentle and fauorable audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the wofull ſtate of your ſayd Countrie of <hi>Prouence,</hi> wherof it may be that your Maieſtie is not fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully aduertiſed. An other is, that good Kings, Princes, and Potenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, haue at al times not only harke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned to the complaintes and griefes of their people, but alſo receiued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and gently diſburdened the Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of ſuch and ſo importunat char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges. The laſt is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in extremities me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to haue free and vnreſtreyned recourſe to him that is onely able to apply the needfull remedye. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto we may ad, that many things are don vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> authoritie of Kings
<pb facs="tcp:26896:25"/> without their knowledg, for which they be now and then diſpleaſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch as haue not aduertiſed them of them. Surely Sir, all theſe conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations haue we ſet afore vs, to the intent that all men may know, that we come not as Mutiners, Rebels, or Sedicious perſons, to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund your treaſure, or to inquyre perticulerly of the imployment ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, or to call in queſtion the faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and vpright dealing of ſuch as haue the ordering of your receytes: but onely to giue you true intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence how great charges, impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, aydes ſubſidies, tallages, taxes, increaſes, &amp; other contributio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, this poore &amp; miſerable third ſtate payeth and beareth. But peraduenture Sir, you will thinke it ſtrange that we which are Deputies for <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,</hi> ſhould alſo interlace the griefs and complaints of the Third eſtate of your Contries of <hi>Languedocke</hi> &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:26896:26"/> 
                  <hi>Dolphenie.</hi> Neuertheleſſe I which am the meſſenger, am aſſiſted by the Deputies of the ſayd Contries here preſent, who gaue me in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion ſo to do as we met to gether by chaunce at <hi>Tarrare,</hi> bycauſe wee had all one meſſage and ſute. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſir, it is done to the intent your Maieſty ſhuld not be troubled with the repetition of like matters. And foraſmuch as our griefes are all vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſelfe ſame points and tend to one ſelfe ſame end: they haue choſen me alone to ſpeake indifferently for all the three countries alike, which thing I haue ſo much the more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly and boldly taken vpon me, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe your highnes hath had expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of my loyaltie, honeſtie, and ſinceritie in your Countrey of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uence,</hi> where it hath pleaſed your Maieſtie to aduaunce me, to one of your chiefe roomes of your Counſel.</p>
               <p>Sir, your Countie of <hi>Prouence</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed
<pb facs="tcp:26896:26"/> of old time to the kyngdome of <hi>Auſtraſie,</hi> and vntill the time of <hi>Reyner</hi> kyng of <hi>Sicili,</hi> who made a gift of it to king <hi>Lewes</hi> the eleuenth, it continued alwayes vnder the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of the Dukes of <hi>Lorraine</hi> &amp; <hi>Barre.</hi> In the time of the ſayd good kyng, (whom ſome haue ſeene that are aliue at this day) the men of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uence</hi> payd not any tallages, impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, ayds, ſubſidies, gables, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther maner of contributions at all, but liued welthely &amp; merely of the reuenues of their demayns, in peace withal their neighbors, and paſſing their time in making thoſe excellent kind of peytings which are yet ſtill to be ſeene in the pallace of <hi>Aix</hi> the chiefe Citie of <hi>Prouence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Kyng <hi>Lewes</hi> at his taking of poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the countrey of <hi>Prouence,</hi> graunted and confirmed all their priuileges which they had in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of good kyng <hi>Reyner,</hi> which conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued
<pb facs="tcp:26896:27"/> ſo to the time of the great king <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt, who vppon neceſſity of the defence of the ſame countrey when <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth came downe into it, made the people therof taxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſubiect to other impoſitions of his Realme.</p>
               <p>The countrey of <hi>Viennoys</hi> &amp; <hi>Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phenie,</hi> at ſuch time as it was ſold to your Maieſties predeceſſors by Sir <hi>Humbert Dolphine,</hi> did enioye like fraunchiſes and liberties as the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of <hi>Prouence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So likewiſe did the countrey of <hi>Languedoc</hi> in the times of <hi>Raymond</hi> &amp; <hi>Berrager</hi> Earles of <hi>Tholouze.</hi> And to ſay the truth, neither taxes, ayds, ſubſidies nor impoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s were heard of, any where throughout all the ſhires of the Realme, till the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhmen had gotten the better part therof, for the diſpoſſeſſing of whoſe vſurpations, our kynges were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned to rayſe great powers and
<pb facs="tcp:26896:27"/> armies of men. And bicauſe the ſoue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raigne dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was held by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhmen: the Frenchmen, (whoſe faythfulneſſe and loyaltie paſſeth al other nations of the earth) grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to kyng <hi>Charles</hi> the ſixth, to tax the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ceaſe them: and that was the firſt time that tallages began, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Regiſters of the Parliament and of the chamber of accompts doo beare record.</p>
               <p>When theſe ſo light Taxes and of ſo ſmall eſtimation could not coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teruaile ſo great an enterpriſe, he deſired the eſtates to help him in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> neceſſitie. Then they gaunted him a Twentith of their wines, &amp; after<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward an Eighth and a Fourth. In the end it came to ſetting of impoſt vppon Salt. And all theſe Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were named helpes, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end of their deuice witneſſeth, which was to take place but ſo long as the Warres laſted, as the Recordes of
<pb facs="tcp:26896:28"/> the ſayd Court and Chamber of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countes do purport. Neuertheleſſe the People of <hi>Fraunce</hi> are ſo obedient to their Kinges, that they haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued the paying of them freely, &amp; are verye wel contented to continue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtill, notwithſtanding y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had ceaſſed for a time after that the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhmen were driuen quite &amp; cleane out of the Realme.</p>
               <p>The great King <hi>Frauncis</hi> who was as ſore vexed and weried with warres as was poſſible, died happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without ouer charging of his peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, ſaying with a cuſtome of the xx. penny ſet vppon the Marchandiſes that went out of the Realme, and w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> certaine tolles ſet vppon the wines, that were brought into the great Townes, wherunto were added cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne tenthes, taken of the Clergie.</p>
               <p>King <hi>Henry</hi> inhaunced againe the Tenths, and eſtabliſhed the rights of Doua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, high paſſage, forreine
<pb facs="tcp:26896:28"/> warres, and forrein Impoſitions. As for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore people, they for their owne ſuccor were charged with no more but Taxe faithfully ordeyned for the payment of the men of War, and yet it is well knowne that the ſayd good Prince was combred w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as many affaires as any Prince. At this daye Sir, it is cleane contrarie to that it was in King <hi>Lewis</hi> the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuenths time. For the ordinarie tax<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es of <hi>Dolphenie</hi> were but lxx. Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Poundes turnoyes, and the taxes of <hi>Languedocke</hi> were ſixe ſcore and twelue Thouſand Pound Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyes.</p>
               <p>In the time of great King <hi>Fraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis,</hi> and at his taking at <hi>Pauie,</hi> they were increaſed: in <hi>Dolphenie</hi> fortie thouſande pound Turnoys, and in <hi>Languedocke</hi> three ſcore &amp; ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand &amp; eight hundred. Which ought to be counted no great matter, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the great need that was for
<pb facs="tcp:26896:29"/> the deliuerance of the king and of the Princes his children.</p>
               <p>Afterwarde in the tyme of kinge <hi>Henrie,</hi> the taxes of <hi>Dolphine</hi> &amp; <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guedocke</hi> were let alone in the ſame ſtate that they were at the deceaſe of King <hi>Frauncis.</hi> Likewiſe alſo were the taxes newly impoſed vpon <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uence,</hi> which were fower ſcore &amp; ſix thouſand pound turnoyes. And at that time the tallage was for <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uence</hi> but two and thirtie thouſand: for <hi>Dolphine</hi> ſeuen and twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand: and for <hi>Languedoc</hi> fiftie two thouſand, three hundred, three ſcore and two pounds turnoyes.</p>
               <p>At the beginning of your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties reigne, which was altogyther peaceable and without ciuill diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the ordinarie taxe of <hi>Langue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docke</hi> was rayſed to fyue hundred and twelue thouſand ſeuen hundred fower ſcore and ten poundes: The taxe of <hi>Prouence</hi> to three hundred,
<pb facs="tcp:26896:29"/> three ſcore &amp; ſixtene thouſand, fower hundred twentie and eight pounds turnoyes, with the increaſes of two, three, &amp; fower ſowſes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pound, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounting to more than a moytie of the foreſaid ſummes. And the talla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are doubled. Vpon euery tonne of wyne is ſet an impoſt of fyue ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. And impoſition is ſet vppon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Oyles by aſſignation of proceſſe. Leuies of money haue bin made now ſix times already by extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie Commiſſioners, and loans as well generall as particular, amoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in <hi>Prouence</hi> to twelue hundred thouſand pound turnoyes, compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending therein the taxes of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes: in <hi>Dolphinie</hi> to nine hundred thouſand poundes: and in <hi>Langue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docke</hi> to more than two millions &amp; three hundred thouſande poundes turnoyes, beſides the vent of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall goods and the tenthes, which is fower times as much as
<pb facs="tcp:26896:30"/> the old taxation was wont to bee, togither with a general ſubſidie ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer erſt ſeſſed vpon the cities &amp; great townes, to be payed in three yeeres, whereof the laſt payment fel out the laſt yeere, and a new cuſtome is ſet vpon cloth. We ſpeake not of other ſmall gatheringes of money y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue bin made in thoſe three. Shyres for the waging, furniſhinge, and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning of men of war during theſe ciuill troubles. But the ſtraunge thinges that haue bin done in the playne Countrie, and the fyning &amp; raunſoming of the poore people in the ſayd Shyres, dooth in eſtimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on exceede all the taxes, increaces, helpes, ſubſidies, impoſitions, and all other leuyings, ordinarie and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie. For if the Souldiour were not payed his wages, he burſt out intoo all licentiouſeneſſe of pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, pollinge, oppreſſinge, raunſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and other outrages which ar
<pb facs="tcp:26896:30"/> not wont to be done in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ntries of enemies or of conqueſt. See I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeche you, howe youre Maieſties poore people haue their fatte, their fleſh, and their bloude drayned from them. Let your highneſſe thinke you ſee a true anatomie of a mans bodie, whereof there remayneth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but ſkinne and bones, &amp; yet thoſe alſo all too torne and broozed. For your people reſembleth it with great compaſſion, deſiring too bee relieued and ſtrengthened agayne, which thing can not bee among ſo many impoſitions, &amp; ſpecially with warre. A true King is lykened to a good Shepherd, whoſe propertie it is to fleece his ſheepe, but not too flea them.</p>
               <p>Wherfore your Maieſties people of the third ſtate of thoſe three poore and deſolate Countries, doe moſte humbly beſeeche your Highneſſe to vouchſafe to prouide for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> generall
<pb facs="tcp:26896:31"/> pacification of theſe troubles, and to haue regard of the miſeries, ruines, pouertie, calamities, deſolations, murthers, waſtinges, ſackinges of townes, hauockes, exactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, pillinges, ranſominges, miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheues, forcing of wiues, deflouring of maydens, and other wickedneſſes comming thervppon: and to bring the ſayd ſhyres again to good tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilitie vnion and concord, by ſuch meanes as your Maieſtie ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue moſt reaſonable: for other wiſe it is impoſſible for men too liue in ſuch diſorder as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vngratiouſneſſe of the time hath brought vppon the ſayd ſhyres, which are drayned ſo drye both of money and means, that the people of the ſayd third ſtate can hardly ſhift to liue, bycauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> men of warre haue pilled and fleeſed awaye all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer is, ſo as there remayneth not any great Cattel or money for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people to helpe them ſelues w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>all</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26896:31"/>
               <p>Theſe are the cauſes that driue vs to ſue vnto your Maieſtye, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the thyrd eſtate of the ſayde Countries for theſe ſixe Yeares of the ſayde taxes, Increaces, and other Subſidies and of all other impoſitions both ordinarie and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, and after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde terme of ſix years, to bring all thinges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to the ſtate that they were at in the time of King <hi>Lewis</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> twelfth or at the leaſtwiſe vnder the reigne of <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt. Neuertheleſſe, in caſes of neceſſity, euen during y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd terme the people of the ſayde Third eſtate, doe willingly offer your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie all their goodes &amp; their liues without reſtraint. Which ſute we beſeech your Highneſſe to wey well, and to apoynte ſome truſtie &amp; fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men of authoritie, to inquire to what vſes ſo great ſumes of money hitherto leuyed of your people haue bene imployed, and to cauſe the men
<pb facs="tcp:26896:32"/> of warre to be well payd hereafter, which is the onely meanes to make them liue in order vnder good rule and warlike diſcipline: and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the ſayde thirde Eſtate, will praye to GOD for the preſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and increaſe of your highneſſe in all proſperitie and health.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="kings_answer">
               <head>¶ <hi>The Kings aunſwere to the</hi> Deputies of the third State of the <hi>three Countries of <hi>Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phine, Languedocke, and</hi>
                  </hi> Prouence.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE King hath taken in very good parte the complaintes, griefes, and requeſts made by the deputies of the third ſtate of the Countries of Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guedocke, Dolphine, and Prouince, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſureth them that he will relieue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as ſoone
<pb facs="tcp:26896:32"/> as his affaires may giue him leaue. It mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelouſly greeueth his Maieſtie, that his poore people haue ſuffered ſo many wrong full troubles. For the appeaſing whereof he hath cauſed his Edict to be proclaymed, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to haue it kept, and will to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt of his power reache out his hand yit further to a greater pacification. And his ſayde maieſtie doeth all his ſubiectes to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that he is charged with allowances to the Princes his bretherne, and of the Ladies his Siſters, with the interteyne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Queene, with the dowries of his mother and of the Scottish Queene, with the allowances of the old Queene Elinor, &amp; of the Ducheſſes of Berrey and Ferrara, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>with the kyngs his Grandfather and Father were not charged, ouer and beſides an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit maſſe of dettes, wherof the ſayd kyngs his Graundfather and Father left him in ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rerages: which things haue ben the cauſe of his further charging of his ſaide people, to his great grief.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Made to Villiers-Cotterets <date>the 18. of October. 1573.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="answer_and_notification">
               <pb facs="tcp:26896:33"/>
               <head>¶ The aunſwere and aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement of the Lord Lodowicke Earle of Naſſau to the Kyng.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Lord Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowicke Earle of Naſſau, for the zeale which hee hath of the good ſucceſſe of the kynges Maieſties affaires, hauing not long agoe talked freely and plainely with the Lords of Schombert and Fregouza at Frankford, and afterward with the ſayd Lord Schombert at Caſſel, thought that his Maieſtie shold haue had intellige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of all, as well by the letters of the ſayd Lord Schombert, as by word of mouth of the ſaid Fregouza, hoping alſo that hee would haue taken all things in good part, according as it proceeded from a hart that was at his com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundement. Neuertheleſſe the ſayd Earle perceiueth by inſtructions from the ſayde Fregouza lately roturned vnto him, and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtandeth throughly by his wordes, that his Maieſtie taketh all things as though hee had ment to bridle him in his owne Realme. VVherein notwithſtanding, it was the ſaid
<pb facs="tcp:26896:33"/> Earles intent but to shew his Maieſtie freely and vprightly, the only meanes whereby he knew he might attaine to the thing that he pretended, which was to knit a firme friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship and good league with the Proteſtant Princes, and to put away and bury the euill report that went of his Maieſtie, as well by common deuiſes of pictures, as by reproch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Bookes, and finally to aſſure him ſelfe of good aid againſt the kyng of Spaine, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he eſpieth dayly diuers euill meanings to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him. And foraſmuch as his Maieſties ſayd miſtaking of things hath cauſed the ſayd Earle to feare, leaſt he were not infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of the thing which hee woulde fayneſt haue him to know, and which hee thinketh in ſound conſcience to be the fitteſt waye to bring the thing to paſſe which his Maieſtie pretendeth: he hath diſpatched to him the Lord Chaſtelier, to informe him more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly of his meaning, and of the thinges which he ſeeth to be expedient for the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paſsing of his deſire, Humbly beſeechinge his Maieſtie to beleue that his ſo doing, is not vppon any peculiar paſsion, or for any affection that he hath to any other thing, than to ſee him in better eſtimation and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation than he is among ſtrange Princes and Potentates, and further of from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction
<pb facs="tcp:26896:34"/> that preaſeth hard at his heeles.</p>
               <p>The meanes for him to come to the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd ends with the ſayd Proteſtant Princes, and to recouer the reputation wherof the former outrages haue bereft him, is that his Maieſtie should firſt and formeſt ſurceaſe his warres againſt them of the Religion, which is the true and onely ground woorke whereuppon he may build his reputation new againe, &amp; whatſoeuer he liſteth beſides with the Proteſtant Princes. For otherwiſe it is impoſsible for him to preuayle.</p>
               <p>And it is no brideling of his Maieſtie, but a receiuing of fauour at his hand, when the ſayd Princes may ſo truſt in him as in them ſelues, and shall ſee in good earneſt that there lurketh none euill meaning towardes them: which thing cannot be, ſo long as his Maieſtie shall perſecute them of the ſame Religion in his Realme, whereof the ſayde Princes make profeſsion, and whereuppon they ground themſelues. By reaſon wherof they can neuer hope for any ſtedfaſt friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship or league with his Maieſtie, ſo long as he sheweth him ſelfe ſo ſore againſt them in the chiefe poynt, namely Religion, which is the thinge that ouer ruleth the doinges of men. VVherefore it is requiſite to giue his Maieſtie a Blanke wheron he might conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually
<pb facs="tcp:26896:34"/> ſet his eye, that firſt and formeſt he let the Proteſtants alone in peace.</p>
               <p>And to the end that his Maieſtie shoulde thinke, that theſe be no diſcourſes in the aire: the ſayd Earle beſeecheth him to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that the ſame had ben the welſpring of all his reputation: and to call to mind what he had ſayd to his hignes the firſt day of his comming to Bloys, in the euening and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other times duringe the treatie of the king of Nauarres mariage, namely that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as his Maieſty had labored ſo much to ſet peace among his ſubiectes, and freely graunted the Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts the exerciſe of their Religion: the ſayd Lords and Princes deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to be mayntained in like libertie, bare him ſo hartie good will, that in deuiſing ere whiles among themſelues who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they might wish to be their Lord (if the caſe shoulde ſo fall out as to come to election) they deſired his Maieſtie with one mind, wishing his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauncement and increaſe, and hauing not any thing more common in their mouthes than his prayſes. VVhereuppon the ſayde Earle ſayd vnto his Maieſtie, that he hoped one day to ſee the imperiall Crowne vppon hiſ head, and that his Maieſtie might beleue that that ſaying of his came not of himſelf, but of ſuch as hauing the authoritie and
<pb facs="tcp:26896:35"/> power to do it, made their full accompt to chuſe him to be kyng of Romanes. VVher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his Maieſtie should haue this aduantage, that wheras other Princes were wont to buy and purchace it by all meanes, and to offer all maner of condicions of aduauntage that they could deuiſe for the purpoſe, (like as the Emperour now preſent, his Maieſties fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in law had neuer ben choſen without earneſt ſute and ſolemne promiſes made, wherof one among many other was that hee ſware to maintaine euery man in freedome of conſcience and exerciſe of the Religion:) his Maieſtie should bee intreated and ſued vnto, to take that great dignitie vpon him.</p>
               <p>That was the very cauſe why they of the lowe cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treys perceiuing their Prince to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>part fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his promiſes, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the condicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s whereunto he was bound, &amp; that on the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary part, his Maieſtie vſed his ſubiectes ſo louingly: wished withall their hearts to haue him to their ſoueraigne Lord, caſting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into his armes, to the end to haue the freedome of their conſciences and the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of their religion, and generally to inioy the ſelfſame benefit which his Maieſties ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iectes then did by his permiſsion.</p>
               <p>It was the ſelfſame and the chiefeſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that moued the Queene of England to
<pb facs="tcp:26896:35"/> make league with his Maieſtie a litle before the murther.</p>
               <p>But now contrariwiſe his Maieſtie is nere his fall, his ſtate is weakened on all ſides, and he is as it were abandoned to the praye to whoſoeuer liſteth to take it bycauſe that through his laſt outrage and former warres made to force the conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of his ſubiects, he is ſo deſtitute of noble men and men of warre, yea and of the ſtrongeſt fortreſſe or hold of his Realme, which is the loue and good will of his ſubiectes, that he is become like an old houſe, that is dayly shored vp with ſome proppes, and yit in the end can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be kept from falling downe.</p>
               <p>His Maieſtie maye ſee how the Spanishe kyng his mortall enemie maketh his hand of the backwardneſſe of his eſtate, laughing with open mouth at his miſfortunes, and imploying al his ſtudie, &amp; indeuer to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne trouble in his realme: aſſuringe him ſelfe (and not without good cauſe) that it is the onely meanes to attayne to his purpoſe without ſtroke ſtryking, ſith that the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard hath more weakened his Maieſtie by the former warres, late ſlaughter &amp; preſent troubles, than if he had made thirtie yeeres warre againſt him himſelfe. Furthermore, the Spaniard ſerueth his owne turne againſt
<pb facs="tcp:26896:36"/> his Maieſtie euery where where he can, with the late outrage, as he did alate in Poleland as his Maieſtie vnderſtandeth well ynough: and the ſame was the only cauſe of courteſie and faithfulneſſe which the Duke of Alua vſed towardes the ſayd Earle at his goinge out of Mons, as he himſelfe reported to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers afterward, namely that hee did it to shew that hee would not commit ſo foule a trecherie as the French kyng had done, and that he was not ſory for the Admirals miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunce, bycauſe hee was the kyng his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters deadly enemy, but yit hee had leuer to haue loſt both his armes, than to haue done that deede.</p>
               <p>And if his Maieſtie continue his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of making warre againſt the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, and wil not ſuffer them in his realm: the ſayd Earle can aſſure him, that the Duke his brother leauing him in that plight to goe into Polonia, shall neuer bee welcome thither. But the people of that cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to ſet them in a broyle as Fraunce is, will count him but as a cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher in Agrim, and the Princes of the land, in ſteed of comming foorth euery where to meete him on the waye for his honor, will drawne back a ten leagues of for feare to ſee him. And contrary wyſe, if he make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:26896:36"/> a meane of good peace in Fraunce be, fore he goe thence, he shalbee receyued, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and honored as much as hart can think-and the foreſayd Princes will wayte for him by the way, to doe him all the honor and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnitie in receiuing him, that they can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe.</p>
               <p>And ſo long as his Maieſtie abydeth in the ſame mind that he is in at this day, the ſayd Earle ſeeth not that it is to any purpoſe for him to hope that the Prince Elector the Palſgraue should ſend to the Queene of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland for the accomplishing of mariage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene hir and the Duke: and much leſſe that the ſayd prince Elector should conſent that the Prince Caſimire his ſonne should ſerue his Maieſtie: for the ſayde Earle was ſure that it shold ſmally boote him to moue the matter, neither could he doe it with a ſafe conſcience, ſo longe as his Maieſtie is in armes againſt the proteſtants.</p>
               <p>His Maieſtie hath all occaſions that can be wished to drawe awaye his armed hande from his ſubiectes, and to ceaſſe his warres againſt them, beſides that the Duke his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the choſen king of Polonia, if hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be well receyued, and to aſſure thoſe country men, that his being among them, shall not be to trouble them or to diſquiet
<pb facs="tcp:26896:37"/> their conſciences, but to maintaine them in the freedome wherein hee found them, may alſo as the Duke his brother, vppon like oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion make meanes to his Maieſtie, not to diſquiet the proteſtantes: and that if they depart otherwyſe, the one into Poland, and the other into Englande: beſydes that it should fall out ill for them ſelues in reſpect of the reaſons aforeſayd, they should leaue his Maieſtie with ſuch a warre vppon his hand as should be ſo much the more harde and daungerouſe, in reſpect of the abateme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his power, with the ſmalneſſe of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and (which worſe is) for that he should not haue any man whom hee might truſte with the leading of his armie, for as much as ſome are too ſeruiſable and affectioned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Spanish King as his feed men, &amp; his Maieſtie could not truſt any man by reaſon of the things that had paſſed.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, the ſayd Earle could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get to aduertiſe his maieſtie, that beyond the ſeas men began to bee greeued at the French fashions, and to waxe loth to deale with them, bycauſe they bewray themſelues to goe vnſoundly to worke, and to ſeeke for nothing but diſsimulation: as not long ago whyle the Queene of England was delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vppon the treatie of mariage betweene
<pb facs="tcp:26896:37"/> hir Maieſtie and the Duke, in the meane whyle shippes of warre were ſent priuily in to Scotlande, to ſtirre vp and mayntayne troubles there, and to make them ſpred by little and little into England.</p>
               <p>Agayne, the brute goeth commonly here, that the men whom his Maieſtie ſendeth abroad, are all of them ſpies which come to diſcouer what is done in princes houſes, &amp; moreouer that all the diſcourſes which his Maieſtie maketh with Ambaſſadours, (ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the name of the Pope) and all the diſpatches which he maketh vnto Rome, are but tales and colours of aſſurance of good will, too ouerthrowe the proteſtantes on all ſydes, and namely the foreſayd princes.</p>
               <p>And that there appeareth ſo much diſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation and vntruth in his maieſties let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and wordes, as men cannot tell howe to truſt them in any good caſe: lyke as in his letters written to the ſayd princes vpon the wounding of the Lord Admirall, when hee had giuen them to vnderſtande that he was ſore diſpleaſed at the receyt of ſuche a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunce, and would make ſuch an example of iuſtice of it, as shoulde bee remembered while the world indured: A two dayes after, he cauſed it to be proclaymed that it was his owne dooing.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26896:38"/>
               <p>Furthermore, how much aſſurance ſo euer his maieſtie gaue after the death of the ſayd L. Admirall throughout all places of his do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minion, that he meant not neyther would, that any man should by any meanes alter his Edict of pacification: it can not in any wyſe agree with the warre which he maketh preſently againſt his ſubiectes of the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and much leſſe with his own ſaying that he would not ſuffer any other Religion tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his owne within his realme.</p>
               <p>By reaſon of which perſuaſions, the prince cannot thinke that his Maieſties promiſing to ſuccour him in the offer which he cauſed to be made to the ſayd Earle without condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, was ſpoken with a playnmeaning hart, but rather feareth that the ſame proceeded out of the ſelfeſame shopp that the former things came, becauſe that in the letters of the Spanishe Ambaſſadour which were ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed a while agoe as they were comminge out of Fraunce to the Duke of Alua, it was ſeene that the Queene mother vſed ſuche ſpeech as this: I cannot thinke that theſe ſo good Chriſtians will make any agreement with the Heretikes: shee ſpake thoſe words of the Prince to his hinderaunce, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is vnlykely that there was any good meaning towards the furtherance of his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26896:38"/>
               <p>The ſaid Earle beſecheth his Maieſtie yit further, to ſet before his eyes what hee hath oftentymes tolde him of the Cardinall of Lorreine: namely, that his dooings were ſo ſuſpiciouſe on all ſydes, that whereas he was in credit with his Maieſtie, and had the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of all his affaires, it was not too bee thought (ſo farre as could bee ſeene) that hee would deale ſoundly or vncorruptly in any thing, by reaſon of the great priuitie which he had with the Spaniardes: yea and muche leſſe, in aſmuch as it is reported, that he hath offered his maieſtie a great ſumme of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, to imploy it againſt the proteſtants.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, the ſayd Earle beſeecheth his Maieſtie to call to mynd, what his highneſſe hath ſayd vnto him ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times: namely, that he conſidered well the miſchiefes that had aſſayled him on all ſydes, and that if hee might by Gods grace once remedie them, by the peace which he hath payned himſelf ſo much to make, he would take good heed, that he fell no more into them. For wheras he is at this hower further ouer the shoes tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer he was, through the counſell of ſuch as vnder his name doe bring thoſe in ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which are called the heads of the factio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and prouoke him to make cleane riddance of them by what meanes ſo euer it bee, as hee
<pb facs="tcp:26896:39"/> dyd by the laſt ſlaughter: his Maieſtie maye wel ſee, it was not to leaue of ſo, but to make him bathe himſelfe more than before in the bloud of his poore ſubiectes, to the ende to haſten his own ruine the more, wherof they haue layd the platt a long tyme afore hand: which ſkarre his maieſtie may yet for al this heale vp agayne, by making a good peace in his realme, &amp; by ceaſsing to trouble his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes of the reformed religion.</p>
               <p>Finally, the ſayd Earle deſireth his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie to bethinke him of this poynt, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he had taken all the townes that are hild by the Proteſtantes in his Realme, yit should hee not haue rooted out the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and to conſider alſo, that the late Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour Charles the fifth did not onely take the townes, but alſo had the perſones in his hands that did ſet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues againſt his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedings, ſeazed vpon their landes, and beate downe their fortreſſes, and yit for all that could nor driue the Religion out of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie, becauſe it is a thing ſo rooted in mennes hartes, that it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be weeded out by force of armes.</p>
               <p>VVherefore the ſayd Earle moſt humbly beſeecheth his Maieſtie, to take theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in as good part, as the Earle hath with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out paſsion or particular affection, ſoundly,
<pb facs="tcp:26896:39"/> truly, and with good conſcience commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Lord of Chaſtelier to preferre them to his vnderſtanding, and to wey them and conſider them well and throughly, not ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring himſelfe to be flattered by ſuch as play the leud Phiſitions, which tell not their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient the leaſt part of his diſeaſe, wherevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon followeth his vndoing, but rather cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diting ſuch as ſeeke nothing but his good furtherance and great increaſe. If hee do ſo: his affaires shal haue as good ſucceſſe, as he would wishe. If not, but that he continue ſtil in his former behauiour: all that euer he can doo shall but turne to his vndoing, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>battell both God and men ſtill more and more againſt him.</p>
               <trailer>¶ FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb facs="tcp:26896:40"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:26896:40"/>
               <head>Concerning the concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and effect that hath enſued of theſe requeſtes and aduiſes, and touching rhe deceaſe of the French Kyng.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is good for</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes to truſt and pray that Kyngs shall liue. It is good for Kynges to thinke and knowe that kynges may and muſt die. Many haue bin the examples therof, and great is the fruite to the wiſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiderers. Gods is the iudgement and execution, mannes is the good or harme as God is to diſpoſe in wrath or fauour. The end is Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. It is therfore good for all, euen the higheſt, to feare God, and to gouerne ſubiectes as Gods people. And ſweete is the comfort to thoſe noble Princes, whoſe hearts and conſciences the ſpirite of God feelingly aſſureth, that they haue lead their people in truth, holden them in Iuſtice, and preſerued them in mercy and equitie. Let the one Realme of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, in their Kyngs, their ſubiectes,
<pb facs="tcp:26896:41"/> and their ſtate, preach to Chriſtendome the mortalitie of kyngs, the miſeries of ciuill warres, the loſſes by diſloyaltie of word and deede, the fruits of truth, right, and peace. Gods is the iuſtice, and iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, whoſe be the honour of all things ſeeming to men good or euill.</p>
               <p>The valiant and famous French king Henry the ſecond, when he was in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt apparance of felicitie and ioye, in the entric of peace, in the feaſtes of mariage, in the very actes of triumph, and euen than when after execution of ſundry for the cauſe of conſcience he had Annas du Burg and other counſellers of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of Paris in priſon, whom for their Religion he thought meete and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to haue put to death, was hurt and ſlaine, to the great loſſe, diſſolution &amp; lamentation of that mightie kingdome.</p>
               <p>His ſonne Francis the ſecond, enriched with one kingdome more than euer his father or his aunceſtors enioyed, the Realme of Scotland, when after execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:26896:41"/> of many perſons vppon the tumult of Amboiſe, &amp; the death of the Vidame of Chartres, he had the prince of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, Madame de Roye, and other noble per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons &amp; gentlemen, priſoners in the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile of Paris and elſewhere, was ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken away by the hand of God to the great deſtitution and ſorow of thoſe that depended vppon his Maieſtie.</p>
               <p>Charles the ninth, now lately deceaſed ſecond ſonne of King Henry, and yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Brother to the ſayd Frauncis, when he thought himſelfe deliuered of thoſe whom he ſuppoſed daungerous to his eſtate, and whom he charged with moſt haynous conſpiracie, found afterward mightie reſiſtance by the remnants of that execution, by whom theſe Articles of requeſt were preſented vnto him: whereuppon hath not followed ſuch full concluſion as had ben to bee wished for the quiet of that kyngdom. Since which time, and the lamentable troubles depen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding, when the ſayd kyng had his owne
<pb facs="tcp:26896:42"/> Brother, with the next Prince of his bloud, his greateſt Mareshals of his Realme, and a number of noble men, in cuſtodie and priſon, and dayly expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was of a totall deſtruction of ſome part of his ſubiectes, God hath added him to his aunceſters.</p>
               <p>The circumſtances of his diſeaſe, the cauſe, occaſion and maner of his death, pertayneth not to vs. It was the woorke of God. No doubt, hee lacked not the care of a mother, the counſell of Phiſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and cunning perſons, the helpe, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe, wish and praier of the famous king his brother, and all that men might do. But Kynges who to vs in reſemblance are Gods, to them ſelues in Nature be men. God giue to all Princes, not that opinion onely, but alſo that cogitation, both to thinke it, and thinke vppon it. God giue quiet to that chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> region of our neighbours, and an hart to all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gouernour:, to haue care of the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and peace of their poſteritie. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
<pb facs="tcp:26896:42"/> all poſteritie there is a Kyng of Kynges to be aunſwered, And GOD giue vs Englishmen quiet and thankfull hartes, that we may reſt in vnitie, cleaue to preſent ſtate, abhorre changes, and ſo vſe our Religion that God find it not neceſſary to withdraw our higheſt treaſure. Amen.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26896:43"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:26896:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
